Guide to the James Tiroff Notebooks and Art Works
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Tiroff notebooks and art works
1962-1966
YCAL MSS 358
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.5
(4 boxes)
The James Tiroff notebooks and art works document Tiroff's experiences touring Europe as an actor and designer with the avant-garde theatre company the Living Theatre between 1964 and 1966.
Tiroff, James, 1939-1975
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Maggs Brothers Ltd.on the Adele Gutman Nathan Theatrical Collection Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
James Tiroff (1939-1975)
James Francis Tiroff was born in Alice, Texas, in 1939. A visual artist, musician, and theatre designer and performer, he was a member of the Living Theatre from the late 1950s, and toured Europe with the company in the 1960s. Before travelling to Europe, Tiroff became a Universal Life Church minister, and was referred to by company members as Reverend Jim. He died of a heroin overdose in 1975.
Scope and Contents
The James Tiroff Notebooks and Art Works document Tiroff's experiences in Europe as an actor and designer with the avant-garde theatre company the Living Theatre between 1964 and 1966. During these years the company was "in exile" from its home base in New York City, following a guilty verdict against directors Julian Beck and Judith Malina on charges of federal tax evasion. They lost their appeal and served sixty and thirty days, respectively, while the company remained in Europe. Tiroff's ten notebooks contain diary entries describing the Living Theatre company travels, rehearsals, and performances. Notes of company meetings and discussions on a variety of topics often include quotes from Beck and Malina. Productions documented in the notebooks include The Brig, The Balcony, The Maids, Frankenstein, Mysteries and Smaller Pieces. Tiroff also details his personal experiences with fellow company members and acquaintances including preparation of meals, impromptu music sessions, sexual encounters, alcohol and drug use, and confrontations with police.
Accompanying the diary accounts (and frequently forming collages within the notebooks) are letters to Tiroff from friends and family members; photographs of Tiroff and others; pen and ink and watercolor abstract illustrations and drawings of people, production costumes and sets, and theatre floor plans; and ephemera including performance programs and handbills, train schedules, ticket stubs, hotel business cards, postcards, and newspaper clippings, maps, and organic material. Several letters from Malina and Beck in January of 1965, during their incarceration in the United States, sent to company members in Belgium, describe how set and costume designs should be constructed for The Maids. One folder of Living Theatre performance programs and Tiroff's Italian motorcycle registration papers follow the notebooks. Tiroff's art works within sketchbooks and as single sheets include pen-and-ink drawings of Living Theatre productions, nudes, and oil and watercolor portraits, including one self-portrait.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Notebooks, 1962-1966. II. Art Works, 1965-1966.
Costume design; Counterculture; Experimental theater -- United States -- 20th Century; Nineteen sixties; Set designers; Theaters -- Stage-setting and scenery; Collages (visual works); Drawings (visual works); Portraits; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Watercolors (paintings); Beck, Julian, 1925-1985; Malina, Judith, 1926-2015; Tiroff, James, 1939-1975; Living Theatre (New York, N.Y.)
- Notebooks, 1962-1966; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Notebooks, 1964 August- 1965 August (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - Notebooks, 1965 August - 1966 August (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
  - Living Theatre performance programs, 1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Italian motorcycle registration, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Art Works, 1965-1966; Series II; 0.67; (2 boxes)
  Arranged by type and date of work.
  - Pen-and-ink/watercolor/crayon drawings (loose and bound in sketchbooks), 1965-1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 13-20)
  - Oil/watercolor portraits, 1965, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Watercolor portraits, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Oil/watercolor/pen-and-ink drawings, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 23)